A few weeks ago, I got a lot of flack
because I released a video going over a
study, this study, that indicated that
butter accelerated cancer growth
in mice. And right about there is where
many people tuned out of the original
analysis, like Bobby here. And Jorgan
didn't even make it that far. However,
while it is true that video was focused
on mechanisms based on mostly animals, I
always try to find evidence to
corroborate or refute using human
evidence, which is why I brought up this
additional human study. So, I'd like to
flip the script and focus on this major
study and address this from a different
angle. So, unless you feel like Kenny
here or possibly more like Black here,
let's take a closer look at the human
evidence relating butter with cancer,
discussing what we know and also what we
don't know. And I think you'll be
surprised. Real quick, if funding and
conflicts of interest is vital to you,
they're detailed in the description box.
Okay, what we're talking about here is a
33-year study across three huge groups
of people making up over 200,000
participants. Now, if you have any
background in study methodology or
simply watch enough science videos,
you'll know that a study that lasts that
long and has that many participants is
an
it's an assoc uh it's a it's an
associative study. So, here's another
point where people will tune out and
many might respond like the ever wise
shell derp. Of course, it can't go
ignored that nutritional epidemiology
can be weak forms of evidence, but I
also fully believe that it can have
significant upside and be a powerful
scientific method. And keep in mind that
we're looking at more than one piece of
evidence. So, would you feel more
comfortable ignoring mounting evidence
even in its fledgling state, even if it
might need further work down the road,
or would it be prudent to slowly make
lifestyle changes out of caution? That
choice is entirely up to you. At any
rate, there are unique strengths to this
study, uncommon to many others of the
same type. For one, the researchers
measured nutrition every few years,
which is not common in other studies of
this type.
They usually do single measurements at
the beginning of the study. In addition,
these particular included groups had
their nutrition assessed, but also had
their biological markers assessed to
validate that what they said they
consumed matched where possible. So,
this is as good as it gets, aside from a
randomized control trial, which don't
work for this kind of investigation. The
main point that I want you to understand
here is that this particular study has
bolstered certain weaknesses common to
associative studies as I'll get into
later. It's not all perfect, but it's a
gargantuan effort. Now, because of the
data is a bunch of numbers and many hiss
like vampires hit by holy water when
math is involved. I can't blame them.
I'm the same way. I've created a
simplified graph, but for intellectual
honesty, here's the numerical data as
well for those that know how to read it.
Now, we're looking at three big groups,
and the relationship between increasing
butter consumption and the death from
cancer. That yellow line that goes up
from the 1.0 indicates that there's no
identified risk. So, if the red lines
touch the yellow line, there's no
identified relationship between butter
and cancer. Clearly two of the three
groups do not indicate a relationship.
However, the third as well as the
combination of all the data. So all
three groups pulled indicates an
estimated 12% increased risk of dying
from cancer. And in fact the same was
true when looking at total mortality. So
all causes of death. There was again an
established link between total butter
consumption and overall death. we can
safely assume that at least part of that
link is due to the cancer data that we
just went over. So, is that it? Butter
causes you to die from cancer? No, not
so fast for multiple reasons, but let's
start with this one. There's an
excellent critique brought up by some
commentary about this study by some
other researchers. That critique states
that the researchers combined butter
with margarine blends under the label of
total butter. Now, knowing that and
knowing that these three groups making
the total 200,000 plus group were first
started to be studied back in the early
1990s,
you might know that margarine at that
time contained trans fats. So, trans
fats of the nature that we're discussing
them are especially dangerous and
destructive, unbeknownsted at the time
as they weren't phased out starting
until like the mid 2000s. So, a good 10
to 15 years after data collection
started. Granted, I don't know how much
of the total butter was contaminated
with trans fats containing margarine. If
it's 1%, then the link that we just went
over likely stands. But if it's a more
sizable amount, like 40%, would it
really be fair to blame butter as the
reason for this cancer link? The answer
is most definitely no. So, are we then
doomed to have this potentially weak
data as our only basis? No, not quite.
Because while the margarine mixup was
true for the total butter, it does not
seem to be true for the two other ways
that the researchers sliced the data.
Namely, when consuming butter added to
food or bread and when using butter in
frying and baking. here. Interestingly,
you'll notice that using butter during
baking and frying did not associate with
increased mortality risk. And yet,
adding butter to food and bread does
raise risk. By the way, the exact same
trend was seen for cancer specific
deaths as well. So, this raises an
important question simply
why? Well, we'll get into that next. And
while I realize that you may already be
crosseyed from what we've already been
over, I actually have much more to say,
and I do, including how other fat
sources like canola, soybeans,
safflower, and more relate to our
mortality and cancer risk. Plus, does
age, physical activity, and other
factors change the interpretations and
nuances? Now, I'm covering all that in
the full analysis included for the
Physionic Insiders, of course, along
with an in-depth article, and if you
want to discuss it with me in the next
live session that I do with the
insiders, consider joining. You also get
these perks over here, too. Link to join
the insiders is in the description box.
Anyway, back to the important question
of why. Now, a few possibilities. One,
and this applies to the previous total
butter data that we just went over, too.
This could be due to something called
residual confounding. Essentially,
because we are looking at associations,
we have to adjust or control for
possible factors that would explain the
results that we're detecting. For
example, it could be that people who
consume more butter also consume more
alcohol and that's the real reason that
cancer and mortality risk is raised.
Obviously, there are many factors
accounted for, including alcohol, but
crucially, diet quality, total calorie
intake, family history of cancer, and
physical activity level, among some
other obvious ones. So, could it be
something that isn't on that list? Yeah,
possibly. I will quick add that one
thought might be that the increased risk
might come from something like refined
bread that the butter is added on.
Fortunately, the researchers thought of
that and even when adjusting for that
along with similar other factors, the
relationship between butter and
mortality remained. Still, that doesn't
mean that something else couldn't be
going on here. Otherwise, the
researchers offer some other
explanations like the fact that the
exposure to butter is less frequent when
looking at baking or the amount of
butter actually consumed when cooking is
less than what's added to the pan. I
think that at that point we're getting
into the weeds of the different
possibilities. In the end, the main
point here is that when we remove the
margin contamination issue, there is
still some signal that butter is linked
to cancer and overall mortality.
Now, I will add this actually isn't the
only study that looked at butter and
cancer either. In this analysis, looking
at completely different group of people
by a different group of researchers from
a different country, butter was also
found to be linked to greater cancer
mortality. Interestingly, when replacing
margarine even, however, I should point
out that this study, unlike the main one
that we've been covering, only measured
nutrition at baseline, much like many of
the other associative studies that
you've probably heard of, this is a
definite weakness of that study. Now, as
a final word before we get into the
hopefully nicely packaged takeaway
section, there are also studies that
indicate no increased risk of cancer
mortality with butter consumption. That
is not uncommon or unexpected. For one,
these studies are smaller, so fewer
participants means that there's less
data to detect a relationship if there
is one. In addition, metaanalyses of
associative studies like these are
intend to have a whole array of
different adjustments like the list that
we went over earlier that vary from
study to study included. There's more
that I could say and more that I could
get into, but suffice it to say that if
we'd be critical of the studies that we
went over missing some context or
factors that could explain the
relationship, these studies are even
more at risk of that issue. Like I said,
there's plenty to be said, but as I'm
often reminded, my videos are too long.
Still, I wanted to acknowledge that it
isn't true that all studies point to
butter being a cancer mortality risk.
Still, where does that leave us?
Everything considered,
that's what you probably want to know, I
assume. Well, I have several things to
say here. One, I said this last time,
but 80% of people who were mad at me
didn't finish the video, so I'll say it
again. Although I guess honestly the
same thing is going to happen here. None
of these studies speak to ketogenic
diets. The reality is many might make
that assumption and I don't think it's a
poor assumption, but we don't actually
know if butter is still detrimental to
those outcomes. So, uh, cancer and
overall mortality when a ketogenic state
is an objectively different
physiological state. Number two, it is
true that none of this science is
definitive. There is room for error and
definitely room for nuance. The latter
of which I will get into next. However,
as more data releases, we're not just
dependent on largecale associative
studies, which keep in mind they do
control for many big factors. We also
saw mechanistic direct causitive data
presented in my first video on the
topic. So, you have to ask yourself, do
I believe that these growing lines of
evidence from different perspectives are
all wrong, or is there a possibility
that there's a signal here that butter
is harmful in the context of cancer? Oh,
and I'll quick point out here, we're
also talking about total cancer, so not
looking at very specific types of
cancer. Number three, the mechanistic
studies that I covered last video was
focused on an obesogenic environment,
meaning overweight animals.
Unfortunately, I don't think that we
have overwhelming data to say if butter
is a cancer problem in healthy, normal
weight individuals. There's a signal
here, but it was insufficiently teased
out in these studies that we went over,
and that signal contradicts the animal
research. So, the certainty is currently
more in line with it being at least a
bigger problem in an obesogenic
environment. Number four, notice how we
covered cancer mortality. None of these
studies that we went over covered cancer
occurrence. That means that we don't
know if butter causes cancer based on
these data. It's entirely possible that
it is only a detriment when a person
already has advancing cancer, which
would be in line with the animal
research that we went over. Number five,
in plain English, there's a small signal
that butter is linked to increasing risk
of cancer mortality and overall
mortality. As is often the case, I'd
like to see more data to really plug
some of the holes, but that's where we
currently stand. What you do with that
information is your choice. The most
risk averse would be to reduce butter
consumption, taking into consideration
the caveats from before. Now, Udo the
carnivore has this message for you about
my work. That was in reference to my
last video going over the mechanisms of
butter and cancer. And to Udo's credit,
I'm not entirely convinced that we have
everything figured out on that front, as
I'll explain. But if you'd like to see
more on the direct evidence, just click
here and join Udo the carnivore in
calling my work nonsense. Thanks for
tuning in. I do appreciate it. I'll
catch you in the next one. Till then.